so recently there was a question about
ignorance and how can we approve
tinker's how can we notice it during the
day and I'm going to do I think one of
the manifestations of ignorance is
distracting myself
neck's acts of distraction turning away
from what you feel turning away from
unpleasant things hmm just trying to go
into this Livius state of indolence yeah
okay but it's less pleasant as well it's
just kind of well it's it's not even
specifically pleasant it's more like
just seemingly offers you a break from
pressure so then the pleasure of that
indolence is simply determined by how
much special you are but often it's not
even pleasant so people find himself
both state but then they can't help and
just sort of do this thing they have no
pleasure from it anymore but you still
have to distract yourself from from from
other things that they're not pressuring
you know unpleasantly so you distract
yourself the reason you distract
yourself is because it gives you a big
release from the pressure that you are
yeah genuine you feel but much like like
sensuality it's the same principle because the
it's the same principle because the
release you get from distraction is is
the release that you get through senses
which is what pressures you in the first
place
to the census pressure you and the only
way for you to release from the pressure
is to give into the census more so in
other words nothing changes on the level
of census which is why you're pressured
the only thing the changes then is the
amount of you actively ignoring the
reality of your situation
so things that are distraction think
things in themselves are not a
distraction it's your attitude it finds
distraction in doing certain things and
yes sometimes those things are very
different depending on people it's
always the same thing please yeah so you
try to distract yourself from I mean
just pressure first brush not the
sensuality so you can actually well
that's why that's why the distraction
always leads to further sensuality
that's right
if you are cultivating the basis of that
indolence you're cultivating the values
essentially it's all within the central
being because it's all pertaining to the
senses so can you find the way to
relieve yourself of the pressure of the
senses without engaging with the senses
without and when I say engagement that's
usually what what people kind of do to
distract themselves either find
meaningless tasks or even meaningful
tasks does that have a reason for
perform but you do it for the real
reasons of just distracting yourself
from yourself which is too unpleasant -
so much for burden too much more
pressure or commonly people who distract
himself by just you know I'm not seeking
sensuality specifically
hello garden hang out with friends just
to kill some time watching movies
entertainment nothing like extra sensual
but in itself it's still visual sort of
distraction audible music or music you
know many people just constantly have
music playing in the background so a
silence becomes too pressuring so
head like if we get tired from general
working from works you want to relax see
what sure you get to switch on a movie
because it's music and be a passive just
that yeah but that's the thing so you
realize so what do you want to relax
from basically you've jaded from having
to deal with sense input the whole day
so you're physically tired it's a so you
can simply relax by going to sleep but
then you realize you have a choice there
and you choose to sit for another three
hours of enduring the senses and watch a
movie so it doesn't really relax you cuz
it's not it hasn't taken you away from
the senses like when you fall asleep so
what has happened they're always just
enabled your mind to go into a state of
self ignoring so that's why that's
unwholesome like watching a movie is not
in itself immoral or not virtuous it's
kind of irrelevant but if you do it for
the complete reasons basically of just
self ignoring ignoring the state that
you're in
did you find them relaxing that's why
it's an awesome so it's your reason
behind the whole so if you die from your
senses go to sleep not go back to the
senses and find something they will just
put you in a state of oblivion why are
you so pressured by the same senses is
something more dangerous that as well
this well it's dangerous because you
realize that only true non pressure
relief of that burden is when you're not
dependent on the senses but if you are
cultivating the state of ignoring as
your form of relief that you know in
value that's very much dependent on the
senses so that which which is the only
relief you know it's not a relief at all
so it's making things worse and it is
that's I mean you even inevitably drift
more and more into into valuing
sensuality
sensitive areas yeah because you had
again you have a choice you could have
just went to sleep
but you also had an option to you know
have visual stimulation they will make
you forget about yourself for hour and a
half why then so if the problem is being
why then so if the problem is being
pressured by the senses
why is your form of relief forgetting
about yourself which has nothing to do
with the senses why is that you relief
surely senses are the ones that are
pressuring you your relief should be
have a break from the senses but you
kind of know it sensitive the passion
you yet then the relief that you have
that you value that you cultivate is the
relief of ignoring yourself in regard to
senses and don't do anything about the
senses but the senses are the problem so that's
but the senses are the problem so that's
why it's dangerous
cuz I'll just put you more into
sensuality but it basically makes you
develop even more distorted views of
where the problem is then you start
valuing that state of of self ignoring
of unawareness even when you're not
distracted so that's what delusion is
the hardest to see and hardest to
approve the stickiest so because you
value that oh I just deserve to have a
break okay go and sleep no but I want to
watch a movie why is that so your break
means engagement with sensuality and the
only result of that is no change in the
level of senses how much you engage with
it the result is how much you are
unaware of yourself
so you're cultivating a habit of
unawareness in regard to yourself in you
that you don't mind so even as I said
even when you're not necessarily
distracting yourself that is your view
now will you value an awareness an
opportunity you get you will be unaware
you're narrowing down the recognition of
of your own situation that's why it's so
dangerous and that's why both ill will
and and sensuality are rooted in them
their attitude of delusion tells me
forget my situation and by forgetting
your situation you then you cultivate
then that kind of basis of forgetfulness
in regard to other things that you
shouldn't be forgetting yeah such as
motivation for your actions and
so that's building up that kind of habit
the state of your mind that you're
developing is this inactive mind it is
complete just yeah dull opaque choose
indolent inactive yeah there is
absolutely no no recognition of thinking
going on there there is no right
thinking going on there and that's
that's the whole point the recognizing
that wait why
if senses are the one that are making me
tired why the hold of you that state of
unawareness is my relaxation and then
you realize there's no reason for that
view doesn't hold you because you never
thought about it see if you do start
reflecting upon it and abandon mu then
you realize that absolute 100% alertness
throughout a day cannot make you tired
has nothing to do with your tiredness so
the other words that is never an excuse
them to be unmindful and run away and
that's what we do we say you spent the
whole day practicing mindfulness because
it's not tiring and that's what he said
you can't have too much of mindfulness
you can have too much of pondering too
little pondering too slack too tight but
you can't have too much of mindfulness
it's not tiring good mindfulness
mindfulness and awareness so awareness
is not so why is then awareness felt
like you it's tiring you it's work
because you haven't understood it you're
not doing it right way but you're not
doing it right because you keep
cultivating than the attitude that the
non work and relaxation is unawareness
but there is no reason for that attitude
except you don't have it if just just
present moment what's over here and now
don't think about tomorrow don't think
about it what happened in yesterday yeah
just here what you have just really be
with the music that's all - a zigzag
with the movie be with be with the
sensor sensor experience now
mindfulness is recollecting us of
yesterday and what's in store for you
tomorrow at the same time presently
right here right now that's what
mindfulness is not exclusion of those
things yeah and that's why the Buddha would say
yeah and that's why the Buddha would say
even when you go to bed you go back
mindfully with the thought when you wake
up and then you truly switch off from
the senses you go to sleep
and then you wake up the moment you wake
up you don't need time to pick up your
awareness your awareness is already
there and you can cultivate that if you
don't willingly and consciously choose
to go the paths of an awareness and
distraction and indolence indolence is
laziness lay down this laziness of mine
yeah laziness of mine sir the work of
understanding say what mindfulness is
see if the mind is lazy mine won't be
mindful if the mind is lazy mine won't
have energy to make the effort and
reflect upon things that need to be
reflected upon if the mind is lazy is
not gonna even itself interrogate in
terms of your motivation stuff which is
gonna go along with the path of least
resistance see if the mind is lazy the
those four right strivings are not
present if the mind is lazy there are no
factors of enlightenment being
cultivated if the mind values laziness
and indolence and delusion of that kind
those four energies four powers are not
there they can be but if the mind is not
lazy so again initially you might feel like
so again initially you might feel like
oh if I practice something you feel all
work bound up which is practicing
mindfulness but that's cause you don't
know what mindfulness is but if you work
through that you realize actually
mindfulness is effortless big
collectiveness is effortless
I don't need when it doesn't matter how
tired how physically fatigued
I am bombarded by the unpleasant sort of
enduring of heat called work whatever
else having mind the resting is nothing
to do with it it's my own assumption of
this is what the rest is completely
gratuitous while in reality then what
the only thing that results in two is
unawareness nothing else there is no
actual factual because even after you
watch a movie you have to go and sleep
we didn't have you're really tired
you never really rested yet you have to
go through these motions over to deep
restfulness so to speak is which is
central it escape from pain
the only known escape from pain is to
seeking pleasure sensuality and this is
like a low-key type of that has no
benefit there so if the opposite yeah
there's no benefit thank yous
non-beneficial has some mental images on
the screen or something and even if you
try to mmm even if you try to present oh
it's it's a documentary or something
yeah but is that the real motivation is
there a necessity for it no what's the
motivation of watching it you need a
break yeah break from what from the
senses yes by engaging more with the
senses how does that make sense so
having having a mind which is active or
alert hmm an alert mind it somehow or if
you don't have an inadvertent mind yes
it's quite painful it's quite there's a
lot of work yeah well then we'll compare
the basically ruling in a state of being
dead if you don't practice mindfulness
says I'm dead it says almost coming back
to you
yeah yeah coming to life escaping death
by practicing mindfulness very
collectiveness
so that's what illusion is those little
things you give in you give in to
throughout the day you know I work hard
yes you did I need a break yes you do
how you go about it that's a choice do
you need a break but just sitting
quietly good sleep on you need a break
by entertaining yourself with what with
the senses they've made you tired in the
first place so in terms of making the
mind strong hmm making the mind alert
fully active away constantly presets
virtues the first thing of course and
then is that trying to understand
correctly what that effortless
mindfulness is because if you do
mindfulness with effort it's not the
mindfulness you should be doing or
rather it's not the mindfulness that
needs to be cultivated so you're not
gonna start perfectly right off the bat
but you if you know that you need to
find the mindfulness that is effortless
it doesn't depend on the senses and what
you're tend to and so on then you will
be seeking it so trial and error you can
arrive at it eventually unless so in
your outside not physically burden
enduring elements none of it could be
mentally tiring because none that is
mentally tiring you make you mentally
tiring I wanting to practice on
awareness of it so let's say one is
contemplative hmm I was thinking about
aspect but it's
it's kinda you have to put effort in the
thing that you have to put some energy
there but that's that's not the effort
you can't have you can't expect that
type of thinking of figuring
investigation to happen effortlessly
I'll watch my breath oh yes and then
contemplation is magically occur it
understand again all those notions that
that many people would have of such
practices would be dispelled that they
were just to start reading suitors like
more systematically just read the actual
suitors I mean the many occasions that
we they would say himself like there's
that the famous so doing he said oh what
if what if I were to not think any
unwholesome thought and only think make
effort to think wholesome thoughts and
he spent day night just thinking right
things and not thinking the bad things
and he said tireless energy arose in me
he could think only what he wants so he
was like through work built up that
energy momentum and when he purified his
thinking nothing unwholesome would be
entertained welcomed maintained
encouraged only wholesome then he says
okay what if I were to now call myself
down but not by not thinking or not
paying at it whatever I think it's fine
simply how do I take this step further
and that's the first journal thinking
and pondering did now you develop
calmness on account of not through
cancellation of your thoughts but you
basically rising up finding but calmness
is within the thinking mind but first
you need to develop the thinking mind
correctly so that's why that's women the
that energy is a it's it's a must
effort repetition drilling training and
I said they probably before but I
remember I started you know this is a
layman and you know you have all these
notions in and they would I kept talking
about the training he trains himself as
he trains himself us and in the
beginning I remember I couldn't quite
like what is there to train you either
become enlightened who you're not
enlightened and then you might train
indirectly like you keep the precept you
do the right things but then you
Lichtman happens to you but how do you
train the enlightenment he did not make
sense but then you read the sutras more
and more that's what mataman is rising
above the unenlightened ink things and
the only way you can rise above it is
true manly effort manly strength Magna
determination manly training any
contemplation any contemplation manly
perseverance many patients whatever and
the semen is of the water and so on it's
not poetic but it's making an effort in
investigation yeah nor do they go out
blindly making effort in focusing my
nostrils yeah well what's the result of
that hey why you why exactly whilst the
point it's about understanding freedom
comes out of understand full
understanding is what our country pays
so am i understanding
no one am i making efforts exactly to
understand as any more clearly thinking
towards understanding no well then I can
know for safely the end it I don't
understand but I will not understand for
sure if I don't at least try to understand so
if I don't at least try to understand so
how do I then go about trying to
understand yeah that's how does that
manifest in it as practice see the
suitors and no just read it and then get
inspired on account of it which you know
might will probably happen inevitably
but don't take that to be the goal okay
great now you're inspired now go back to
the same suitor that inspired you so
much and understand it and as I said
many times before you will know if your
understanding the meaning of the Dharma
that the Buddha laid out if you're
becoming incapable to suffer amid
suffering not if you don't suffer at the
moment if the worst thing were to happen
to you how much would you suffer before
you understood what you understood and
now after the understood it that it has
that suffering diminished and you can't
have a sense of it you my god you will
not know exactly how much it diminished
but you will have a sense that I am less
touched by suffering there is less pain
not because I'm running away justifying
psychologizing trying to avoid it simply
because like he cannot touch me so
that's how you become fearless as well
person who doesn't experience fear is
not fearless
yeah person who within like with within
the experience of fear doesn't fear it
he is a fearless one so if you're
constantly hiding or frightening away
from frightening things you don't know
if you're fearless or not because you're
just hiding from fear so how do you know
if you're fearless
you're just fear free at a time but
you're not fear less as an incapable of
being afraid that's a completely
different thing that you can only
develop to understanding you know
overcoming fear make the stench of fear
it's a fear of restraint fear of giving
things up fear of losing your
possessions your attachments your loved
ones so hard honey is the fearless one
incapable of being afraid because he
worked wait he's not brave no no he's no
nice lady Rhea varial you need the fear
yeah and then just go against it so on a
practical level you want to be trying to
understand hmm
the teaching of the Buddha so unique is
gonna be hard like same when you learn
any you're learning any new subject or
something so you have to read the sutras
practice virtue in precepts you go the
greater you your virtues are basically
the creative potential for understanding
you have the what and then you start
reading the sutras in you you will if
you start making effort to understand
them and keep reading and your mind will
get hooked on to different aspects they
will make more sense do you think about
more through and clarify them then
suddenly new aspects become revealed
then you go into them then you go to him
and that should be your meditation as
well as the Buddha said before I was
enlightened while I was still an
enlightened Bodhisattva I decided what
if I were to think only holes in
thoughts and not think unwholesome
thoughts so if you're a puto jinnah not
even near the right view
far from otherhand ship that is the only
thing you should be doing trying to
understand it um any meditation you do
concentration relaxation practice has
nothing to do with the Dhamma because
you have no Dhamma and that's again with
the other right view there is no
meditation so how can you meditate if
you don't know what the meditation is
and that's what I mean in other talks we
covered it about meditation sensuality
have a little title like that's why you
are the only reason you want these
meditation your meditation technique
they make you feel all right and
peaceful and so on is because you want
pleasure you wanna grill agreeable experience
you wanna grill agreeable experience
that's all but which means you're
choosing to not do the work of getting
the right view
so that's how you practice go by yeah if
sometimes thinking gets like it's just
too much so to speak yeah okay relax a
bit but don't start valuing that
relaxation from work because you haven't
done the necessary work there's other
things you can do like if you read a
certain asset you know understand the
body so question what is the body yeah
answer well all of them will become more
apparent once I'm talking about the
absolute beginner who comes there what
do i do once you studied in the sutras
you start getting a sense and then you
can have your own interrogations of the
things that matter you don't need to
constantly be kind of reinvigorated with
the suitors yeah Glyph yeah
both the feeling have a feeling feeling
what is the feeling even when I say
feeling to myself or to somebody else
what am i referring to I mean we've done
those interrogation is that say someone
will be might read the suitor about okay
feeling this feeling's this body there
and read the suitor and then I just
stare that level of inspiration but that
other level of that needs it needs to be
effort made yeah which is painful that's
dead what work what does this mean yeah
what is the meaning here that's
especially if you're not trained in
doing it most people not training doing
it I rather just read the suitor nicely
get a nice feeling from it okay yeah
horrible same thing with all these talks
and stuff saying I mean we try to make
up talks as as kind of engaging as
possible but I'm sure many people would
just be inspired by it and you know
inspired by the energy we put out or
whatever I don't know and not actually on the
I don't know and not actually on the
style all the style the way we speak I
don't know but be that as it may you
need to understand what's being said if
you're just running off on an
inspiration you're not doing the work
and it's even worse because you think
you're doing the work like before at
least you knew you were not doing the
work and you're not doing the work but
now you think you're doing the work
simply by being inspired by not making
effort to understand while you're not
doing the work
so now it's gonna be twice as hard to
snap out of that because but the pretext
of doing work you feel great inspired
damn is so easy or so inspiring but okay
so are you free from suffering on
account of it yeah so there's no
understanding taking place so what are
you inspired about let's buy this it
gives me a nice feeling he's a nice
feeling yeah I'm inspired with pleasure
so then it's inevitable to experience
that when you either leave the suitors
or listen to the Dhamma taught by
somebody you are they gonna prove or
disapprove on that level of your feeling
but if that's your that's as far as you
go your criteria if that's the sole
criteria you are missing out either way
and same by the way when people
disapprove but being said not because of
what's being said this is how it's being
said that's why you you clearly there's
nothing effort understand one minds into
this why is this wrong why do I think
it's wrong it's lies it right yep why
can I tell is it like this this side
journeys right why because he's cooled
yeah why but why why is that right or I
don't like this this is wrong okay why
do you need to know why and that's the
that's the that's the world yeah that's
the part yeah you know I remember when I
was I would take up random books from
the library philosophy books and so on
of clearly things they would be regarded
as wrong views but I will read it to
understand why it's wrong not just to
get off from the righteousness that this
is wrong this is ridiculously wrong yeah
but I need to see why it is wrong no
just oh it's wrong cuz I took it because
oh it's wrong cuz I took it because
somebody else is that I believe in said
so it's not Buddhist or something yeah
well they were like reading in Nevada
and then he would mention all these
other philosophers and they were wrong I
thought but he wouldn't do well on it so
I found some of those books and okay so
I need to see why this is wrong why
need to see for myself I can't just
accept that this is wrong and then
consequently things that you regard is
right you start putting in question and
that's the unpleasant bit o things that
I thought uh you know I understood you
but why how is this right why is this
right is it right because it's
absolutely contradiction free maybe well
maybe there you go you're doubting it
you're not sure so how do you know it's
right yet here you are acting as if you
know it's right that's the practice it's
not coming it's only partially coming
across the right instruction yeah sure
suitors talks but if you never actually
start taking things up on that level
internally making that effort all this
is meaningless
that's the onus wanna scare apart going
back to that origin origin of look of
your views with which you are listening
to this teaching in order to then start
doing it right like what is your
perspective console suspected yeah what
is a consistent yeah what is it based on
what is based upon I have this
perspective on this but when I kind of
what I have such perspective then you
real is more often not in a kind of I'm
finding it pleasing the idea of it this
is whatever pleases me that's why I
assume it is right I told you that again
where as a layman after totally my first
year of reading disorders it was that
indigent ek I think Sammy a power so
tired it was a suited that lists about those
it was a suited that lists about those
six different Roman pajamas no no no no
no no sorry Paula it was the fruits of
the whole life and in dead so to the
Buddha describes the is different like
fundamental other different teachers six
six different teachings about you know
like there is nobody getting killed and
then the simile of cutting the sword
goes through their mind even determinism
I didn't know much about it at the time
and I was reading that so Tate's along so -
I was reading that so Tate's along so -
so by the time I arrived in a bit I was
reading students before that so by the
time I made that suture I didn't read
the leading up sentence when they woulda
said celebrate on this view that said
these are the wrong views I kind of so I
just started reading these suitors and I
thought the Buddha was teaching that and
then yeah of course there is nobody
killed because another you know then the
next one
look the what was that one didn't that I
think it was that
yeah determinism wasn't it the boiler
they will kind of run its course when
you deplete the bad karma in itself by
itself but yeah of course of course
so as I was reading these views I was
accepting all of them thinking the
Buddhist saying that and then when he
finished he said see that's why these
views are wrongly to peddle and oh my
goodness I realized even the stuff that I thought
I realized even the stuff that I thought
I understood about the Buddha and the
teaching of the dominum I didn't because
I just literally accepted six different
wrong views as one as the Dhamma but
fortunately that concern I took on as a
challenge to understand it notice oh I
must cover this up in every day suit
again and just focus on things I think I
understood know why is that determine
isn't wrong and he's just this huge
weight of a peg have no idea where to
stuff I have no idea why it's wrong well
I better start making effort to find out
cuz it is wrong but he made sense an
otter nobody gets killed
what's wrong why don't you just do the
same just in a different way
already enlightened yeah yeah actually
no but I said this is wrong so I do I
had a and again fortunately I had enough
faith even in that initial stage in the
suitors and the Buddha to accept that
which I clearly did not say he is wrong
that it's wrong but not stay that level
it's wrong it's wrong it's wrong but
it's something that needs to be
understood because if by understanding
understanding different wrong views mmm
you can uproot those wrong things that
you yeah you're getting clearer to the
water right view is it's a different way
of progressing but equally valid or
something I was born pretty much
understanding because all the views you
have is a provisional wrong views yeah
so by undoing them means by
understanding them you can arrive with
the right one so it's not optional to go
through that just some people need to do
more of that some people need do less of
them but the work needs to be done
that's the point
let's thing you have yes a you have from
this but you don't even know what they
are you don't know what and even you know we
you don't know what and even you know we
acted the the examples in the suitors of
people practicing out of faith you know
the faith types are the no sorry and so
on
now people often oh I'll just focus on
devotion that's not good faith is faith
is that accepting that the Buddha's
right even if you have no effect you're
proof for it that's your faith but that
faith is relevant and valid only if now
on account of that faith you start doing
the same effort yeah investigation
somebody can't do that just on account
of faith he needs to start making more
effort to even arrive at the point to do
the effort on account of what the Buddha
said some people just hear what the
Buddha said and they'll do it but either
way you need to do it but these days
when you say faith I'm a faith type and
so on just means basically bhakti-yoga
and your devotional worship no there's
nothing to do with faith the Buddha was
teaching faith in a doctor of faith in a
in following a doctor prescription
without comparing it to other doctors
and so on which some people need to do
either way the work needs to be done
that effort needs to be made so
whichever type you are doesn't matter
what matters is the effort
you spoke about a long time ago about
like mental relaxation again hmm and
that's what you must watch out for yep
you never want to give in to that exact
let mental indolence yeah ah I just put
my feet up for five minutes and nothing
about it find another way that's an
awareness and that's something you give
into exactly so see I'm physically tired
I'm physically tired we've been walking
30 kilometers I need to sit down put
this back down that's absolutely fine
you sit down put it back down even go to
sleep but that's where that ends you
choosing an account of that to give to
an awareness that's a completely
unrelated thing for which you're
responsible that's what delusion saying
as we desire it's on it's on you it's
not on the matters domain it's not on
the senses it's not on how tired you are
it's not on the elements so you getting
relaxed in terms of stopping what you're
doing they were tiring you it's fine
but you getting relaxed or taking that
the relaxation then on the level of
becoming unaware in your mind because
you worked so hard that's not fine that
bit is not fine that's like you overly
well coming in now and puttin in doing
it until everybody shouldn't be done
definitely this doesn't mean you must
now contemplate Dhamma furiously no you
don't need to do that either but you
mustn't give to an awareness so you
sometimes it's you know it's even if
this is it Buddha said yeah you might be
making too much effort to figure things
out so you drop the effort to figure
things out but it doesn't mean you drop
your awareness of your situation yeah
look at this because that is effortless
being in the present moment is
effortless because whether you want it
an accurate in the present moment it's
not a matter of choice a recognition of
the world bodies it's not a matter you
already have that knowledge are you
seated now oh let me let me I'll get
back to you and everyone you already
know it's effortless that knowledge you
don't need to be attending Andreea
attending in
and riku like it's already there all you
need to do is stop distracting yourself
from it by making choices and a kind of
sensual diversion and distraction and
delusion so the effortless mindfulness
is not done by you the effortless
mindfulness is basically created by you
not distracting yourself from it not
turning away not turning away from it
yeah not consciously going into oblivion
not consciously going into oblivion
oblivious States yeah yeah that's what
greed aversion delusion and non-greed
non-aboriginal that anything looting
greed avarice delusion they would have
said he won't think he won't entertain
he will not welcome and in sort of
cherish anything that suits the
non-greed none of us knows he will
tireless energy no need to rest day
night because it's it's tireless there's
nothing to do with that which stars you
which is a census
that either way it's going to be work
yeah you need to build it up you need to
build it up it's almost like this
theater you can just even begin a little
bit not even yeah of course yeah
cuz it's horrible in the beginning when
you just bewildered and now you decided
it's just it's it's worse than the
physical work it's not incidentally the
hokum of humanity tends to turn away
from it
turn away from responsibility from
reason turn away from rational thinking
recognition takes effort takes enduring
takes pain takes take some greater
reason to make you go into that
direction of more resistance against the
grain than most people want on do